he breaks Ray Williams's longstanding
ipf raw SWAT world record he said it's
not the day he's capable
of 14 of 24 broke the alltime world
record totals like were the alltime
world records previously just a sham or
is it just a facad are you kidding with
this like it's just insane you know 700
lb pin squats he's doing thousand plus
pound yoke walks just the most
ridiculous stuff you've
seen welcome to strength weekly the
weekly YouTube show that keeps you
updated on everything from around the
barbell game I'm David Thomas to I'm
joined by Phil Blackman make sure you
subscribe to barbin on YouTube I said
all that really quickly because a lot of
stuff happened over the weekend the
biggest first biggest event of the
strength sports calendar happened in
Jolly Old England the Sheffield
powerlifting championships absolute
Insanity actually might be one of the
most historic powerlifting competitions
in history we have the breakdown on that
we're going to talk about Jesus aras's
ipf world record squat we we had to just
pick one lift to like zoom in on so we
picked the heaviest we're going to talk
about someone who might secretly be the
strongest person in the world but
doesn't compete and trains in relative
obscurity Mitchell Hooper has thoughts
on Tom havland out of Australia so we're
going to break that down and then we're
going to wrap things up because H rock
is on a Monumental International growth
tear and is actually expanding to Canada
we're going to talk about why that's
important Phil what is one word you
would use to describe what went down at
Che at the Sheffield unbelievable
literally unbelievable you could there
are athletes who eclipse the total World
Records in their weight category by
several percent several percent and
guess what they didn't finish in the top
five can you imagine you go into an
event you're like okay I've trained all
this time this is the best prep I've
ever had you go in in you shatter the
world record in your weight class and
you're not even in arms length of the
podium not even spitting distance like
not even spitting distance you could
shatter the world record and you're just
nope you're not even you're not even
close to the podium Phil you covered the
Sheffield all weekend have you slept
have you eaten are like is the
adrenaline still coursing through your
veins uh if anything inspired me to get
a barbell in my hands it was everybody
making it seem as the world records are
actually really low and maybe they are
feasible and possible for us civilians
to get because it was nonsensical the
amount of weight that people tolded at
this event so just for context the
Sheffield is an interesting powerlifting
meet there were 24 athletes 12 on the
women's side 12 on the mens you have to
be elite you have to be a potential
world recordbreaker just to even qualify
to get invited here you're competing
across weight categories and it's all
about who is lifting the highest
percentage of the existing world record
total in their weight class so it's a
way to compare athletes across weight
categories the lightest body weights the
medium body weights the heaviest body
weights so you're competing against
everyone you might weigh 150 kilos they
might weigh under 50 kilos but you're
still in the same competition it's a
really cool format it was a Who's Who
and more athletes broke eclipsed the
total world record in their weight class
than didn't at the
Sheffield that's how insane it was over
half of the
competitors beat the existing total
World Records in their weight category
it's unlike anything we've ever seen and
powering is not a new sport in and the
ipf is not a new Federation in any way
shape or form just want to point out the
women's side was especially crazy you
could lift 105% you could add 5% onto
the total world record as some athletes
did and not make the podium at the
Sheffield what is this Phil break it
down for us yeah for for context on how
insane this event was so in order to get
there in the first place at a previous
competition you had to score at least
95% of your weight class's total world
record to even be in the conversation of
getting an invite now contextually e
Corgan uh in the 52 kilogram class for
on the women's side and Jesus oliveres
the super heavyweight on the men's side
were the reigning Champions coming into
the competition Now spoiler alert Jesus
broke the all-time ipf raw squat world
record and came in a out of
12 I'm sorry excuse me what what
happened are what like are you talking
about the ipf world record that like has
stood for years years Ray Williams
record for years not even close not even
in the top like in the bottom like he's
in the bottom he was the defending
Champion comes in at the bottom still
broken alltime world record that we're
gonna talk about okay on the women's
side 12 athletes right 12 athletes
competed on the women's side 11 broke
their all-time world record totals 11
out of 12 11 David that's not real life
that's not real life and then on the on
the men's side the three top Podium
finishers the top three broke the
alltime total World Records so out of 24
athletes 14 of 24 broke the alltime
world record totals like were the
alltime world records previously just a
sham whereas it's just a facade are you
kidding with this like it's just insane
it's just insane man and I've been I've
been knee deep in it all weekend it's
crazy well let's break down the the
podiums let's start with the women's
side the women's side the entire Podium
was 69 kilogram competitors AA Sito
lifted
9.3% of the world record in that weight
category to finish in first she's 21
David she's a junior lifter and this is
not like an immature weight class this
is not like oh the weight body weight
categories were just restructured and
like no no no like these are like these
records have been creeping up slowly for
decades and just to to mark on the 69
kgam class for for what happened here so
lab of wall champions 69 kg powerlifter
she comes in as like expecting to be the
threshold right like she is going to set
the bar AGA Sito comes down a weight
class and Car Gar comes up a weight
class so we have two athletes coming in
from the top and bottom to compete
against Bal at 69 kilograms if any one
of them is in their own competition it's
not close it's just not close gar hit 10
16.1% of the world record total Bal hit
10 16.6% of the world record total and
then sio comes in with
109.3 of the world total like these AR
like I get we're saying numbers but I
don't know if anybody listening to them
fully understands how insane they are to
add 9% to a total world record it's it's
almost unheard of powerlifting
weightlifting are different sports there
obviously three lifts in powerlifting
two in weightlift like they're tough to
compare but that would be a little bit
like Lasha
talakad at his next competition deciding
to snatch 240 kilos instead of 220 kilos
and just deciding to clean in jerk 490
kilos instead of you know 467 like
that's the margin that these records
were extended by right like it's just
something that doesn't hap it just
doesn't happen so the men's side was
interesting so you basically had to
break a world you had to break the world
record in your weight class to Podium
right all three men who did that on the
men's side podiumed just in off the
podium in fourth place was Gavin Adine
he was 0.1% away from the world record
in his weight class two of the other
ones Gustav Hedland and Jonathan Koo
they both eclipsed the world record at
the 93 kgam class by 10.8% and 100.6% so
you come in you're like okay I am so
close I am a breath away from hit from
matching the all-time world record total
of the ipf in my weight class and two
guys are just like yeah whatever dude
we're like that that's we're way past
that shots play like what are you doing
are like how how did you get here just
to back to the women's side and then
we're going to have to move on back to
the women's side the only Sports
accomplishment recent memory that I can
compare to AGA sito's dominance here is
Usain Bolt in like the 2008 Olympics he
extended the world record by just such a
Preposterous degree that like no one the
announcers didn't have anything to say
they're like we didn't we didn't assume
this was possible it's just the mar the
jumping of the margin is so wide gar
went first and like took the world
record total and then seconds later Bal
takes the total and then sio comes in
and just annihilates the total but like
can you imagine your Bal and you just
like you you technically don't have the
world record because you matched the
world record that was hit just literally
seconds before you got onto the podium
this to me makes the Sheffield the most
exciting thing in powerlifting I think I
think Sheffield is the most exciting
thing in powerlifting we're going to
clip this post it on social and people
will come at me in the comments come at
me in the comments let me know what you
think there's a bunch of like very good
like top powerlifting competitions that
get the world's best to try and claim
world records at like all that stuff is
awesome but this event is just this just
moves the mark it just moves the bar so
far check the link in the description
below because it's it's too much to
recap here it's literally too much to
recap on this show so if you want the
full breakdown of all the stuff that
happened at the Sheffield click the
links in the description below in the
video you're watching click them links
because we go into detail Phil we got to
move on but we're not moving quite on
we're gonna talk about Jesus olivz who
didn't have the best day right he's a
defending champion who won the 2023
Sheffield he didn't have the best day he
made all three Squad attempts we're
going to talk about the world record but
he only made one attempt each in the
bench press and the deadlift right yeah
I just want to say like yes he only he
only hit one attempt on each of the
things but like to be fair he hit
96.6% of the total world record in the
super heavyweight Division and set the
ipf raw all time squat world record and
we're like me it was not the best day
mediocre day he he took a social and was
like it's not the best day he's a
defending champ he wants to re toally
totally he said it's not the day he's
capable of yes of course on the squat he
obviously set a new world record let's
talk about that 478 kilos he breaks Ray
Williams's longstanding ipf raw squat
world record uh which was
4775 so not like a huge margin but
breaks that right it's a th53 pounds
over 1,53 pounds massive massive massive
accomplishment yeah so it was a very
longstanding record Ray Williams has
been dominant in the squat for in the
super heavyweight division for a long
time this is an ipf world record there's
a lot of federations in powerlifting so
the actual ual all-time heaviest world
record squat still belongs to Ray
Williams he has a 490 kgam squat in the
super heavyweight division that still
stands as the all-time heaviest so olis
is getting closer to that it's very
possible that in 2024 he could attempt
or Eclipse that he gets the ipf world
record here at the Sheffield and that
was effectively enough to get him pretty
close on just his openers he got 96.6%
of the world record total and on one of
the bench press attempts he he made 255
on his opener and one of his two 75 kilo
attempts on the bench he pressed it he
just racked it before he got the signal
to Rack it which is part of the sport
like I'm not saying that like oh no he
was robbed like that's part of the sport
you have to wait for the signals I get
it just like in weightlifting but it
just shows he he was capable of pressing
it took a valant missed his opening
deadlift at 380 made it on his second
attempt took a valiant effort at
429 right a 49 kilo jump huge jump huge
jump was not able to hit it but you know
what we're going to see him back
exciting lifter to watch
quick shout out too to Amanda Lawrence
we talked about her during last week's
episode she did break the alltime squat
world record for the 84 kilo women but
finished at 11 she her particular
instance is so crazy like okay 12 women
competing she get Amanda Lawrence
multiple time world champion hits 100.3%
of the world record total in her weight
class she breaks the alltime ipf raw
world record in the 84 kilogram class
and gets 11th like are you kidding okay
you you you're you're hyped you break
the world record you hug your coach
you're like we did it our prep was
awesome great success two World Records
boom let's go get some drinks uh how
about 11th shout out to Amanda uh it's
awesome it's really awesome awesome all
right we're gonna move on to other
strong people but someone who's not
really competing Tom havland out of
Australia he's 6'8 nearly 400 lb ripped
by the way imagine if Brian jaw just had
mariio panowski body yes basically
that's it with maybe bigger traps
somehow um bigger traps former
Australian Special Forces uh member of
the Australian Special Forces
trains basically in the outback
effectively alone trains in like cargo
pants and boots training Outdoors rarely
faces a camera he's not we've had very
few looks at his physique or even what
his face looks like he posts on social
and he does insane things absolutely
insane things we he's been on our radar
for a while and then Joe Rogan
highlights him fairly recently on The
Joe Rogan Experience and it's like is
this guy the strongest person in the
world secretly because he doesn't
compete in strong man he's like trained
with people who compete but he does not
really compete you know he's just doing
his thing clearly loves the training and
the process but he's doing thing like
things like
425 pound deadlift to zercher catches so
he's like cleaning it and then catching
it in a zercher he's doing 900 plus
pound de lifts he's doing you know 700
lb pin squats he's doing thousand plus
pound yoke walks just the most
ridiculous stuff you've seen and so
Mitchell Hooper the reigning World's
Strongest Man sat down watched some of
hain's lifts and was like okay
head-to-head who's stronger me or him
I'm the reigning world's strongest man
let's actually look at this right let's
actually Analyze This a bit and compare
as close as we can Hooper broken down
across seven list now some of them
didn't really it's tough to count like
there's not a Max bicep curl in
strongman or it's not very common at
least and like havan had one and Hooper
was like cool I'm just going to compare
his lifts with mine and if there's like
if it's tough to compare we're going to
like give a little Grace on either end
right like so he has Zer carries we have
Conan's wheel let's compare these things
Hooper is extremely good at calibrating
how he racks up against the other strong
men that he competes against at the top
level and even when I've interviewed him
you know and he's talking about like
what his expectations are going into any
given event he's very clearheaded on I
am capable of this amount and I know all
of the other athletes around me are
capable of this amount and so I can
expect to get first place here second
place here a Bronze finish here he's
very very good at that he's his
assessment is one of the sharpest in the
game so him coming and looking at havin
and going this guy actually is just like
on par for a lot of the stuff of where I
am and I'm currently the best in the
world the majority of the events that he
was tracking against each other there
were toss-ups and so now we're all like
if they actually competed against each
other now granted these are training
lifts versus in-competition lifts there
there is competition is a two-edge sword
double-edge SW some people perform
better in competition right some people
perform better because the crowd gets
them pumped like they perform better in
competition some people perform worse
and then sometimes it's hit or miss it
depends like you have sometimes you have
to travel for competition you might be
eating different food be on a different
sleep schedule I also want to point out
strongman's an interesting sport it's
highly specialized and strongman's very
stop and go and for a lot of these
competitions especially where strongest
man you're having to warm up cool down
and then warm back up sometimes even for
the same event because the Heats take so
long right so there are a number of
factors here strongman's incredibly
specialized right there's a lot of stuff
strongman can seem like a hodg Podge at
first but it's actually an incredibly
specialized sport right these are
Athletes Training for specialized
movements and to Excel and be the best
and fine-tune their performance on those
movements right so all that to say like
there's a difference here we're we are
we're not even comparing apples to
oranges we're comparing apples to desk
chairs right but you know one thing I
love about Mitchell Hooper he has fun as
World his reain is world's strongest man
has been fun let's ask some fun
questions let's have fun with it because
at the end of the day this is for
entertainment sport at this level is for
entertainment especially World's
Strongest Man which is a competition
built for TV right let's talk about it
let's analyze it let's have some fun
with it and let's discuss it let's get
some punditry going and I love that
Mitchell Hooper has fully embraced that
one of the things about this this
commentary on havin too is that all of
his training lifts are performed outside
in what can be presumed is pretty heavy
heat and one of the the the the Mainstay
markers of the world's strongest man
competition is that it takes place in
excessively hot environments as somebody
who's covered the world Strongest Man
live for several years now it is hot
like it is not a good environment for
like the heaviest athletes to be lifting
the heaviest things so if havland is
also like really comfortable in that
kind of lifting heavy in that kind of
environment that also is suggestive that
like if he actually like traveled to
Myrtle would qualified and traveled to
Myrtle Beach you know maybe he's running
with the best of them maybe it's a cool
wh if and I just want to say one thing I
really love about the pro strongman
scene it's a tight-knit community now
some athletes beef right there are some
I want don't want to say blood feuds
right but it's not all love all the time
but it's a lot of love a lot of the time
of right and it's a really fun community
and they talk about lifting each other
up right supporting other through hard
times through difficult personal times
right they're like you know if go
through something difficult personally
the first people to reach out and help
are my competitors it's a really cool
environment it's a really cool community
of giant massively strong people and in
a way this is Hooper kind of like
extending a little branch and saying hey
Tom if you're ever interested I'd kind
of love to have you join this this merry
band of giant Misfits is there's a tinge
of that to what Hooper is saying and
it's honestly really hard heartwarming
it's like really I was like there are a
few times Hooper in Hooper's video I was
like oh he's like he's saying that he's
kind of opening an invitation saying Tom
like come be one of if you want to come
be one of us like Open Arms man we'd
love to we'd love to have you push us
we'd love to have we'd love to have you
take some titles right and there's
something really wonderful about that
that I think is often semi unique to the
strength community so shout out to the
strongman Community for actually
exhibiting a lot of love and a lot of
welcoming there well we're going to move
on to a different sport a newer sport
founded in 2017 in Germany High rocks
has grown massively in popularity even
though it's the same thing kind of over
and over again which could be a benefit
could be a downside we'll discuss that
is now expanding to Canada
Phil hrock consist of a one kilometer
run and then a functional fitness
station and there are different ones you
repeat that eight times and that's H
rocks what's a good time for an elite
High Rock athlete what's this like this
barrier that people talk about if an
athlete runs the a high rock race in
approximately an hour like if they can
get a sub hour time that's Elite you're
an elite you're an elite level hro
Runner if you can get a sub hour time so
uh for anybody who doesn't know what
hyrox is or or has never actually seen a
hro race before the eight stations that
are interspersed with 1 kilometer runs
are a 1,000 meter ski urg a 50 meter
sled push a 50 meter sled pull an 80
meter Burpee broad jump circuit a 1,00
meter row 20 100 meters of a farmer's
carry 100 meters on sandbag lunges and
then 75 or 100 wall balls depending on
which division you're in 75 for the
women 100 for the men it's heavy on the
endurance there is a strength component
right um because going to failure on the
movements means you're out you're you're
basically not competing right you
basically need to do these movements
pretty much unbroken is is what it's
what you're looking at but a heavy heavy
bias on the endurance component we've
seen High Rock siphon off some athletes
from the CrossFit world who are focusing
more specifically on high rocks now
we've seen it grow a lot in popularity
uh Phil we have some percentages on like
high Rock's growth obviously from the
brand so they're going to highlight
their percentages we actually have
interviewed their founder on the podcast
barbin podcast before what are some
numbers as far as like H Rock's growth
since it was founded almost seven years
ago at this point over the last five
years participation has jumped over a
thousand per on in hro races now the
cool thing about hrock Races by
comparison to any any other functional
fitness sport like CrossFit is that the
race the highrock race that we just
talked about is the same everywhere in
the world so regardless of where you
compete or when you compete the race is
the same so when you run multiple times
you might have a particular time on a
race you'll get another shot to do that
exact same High Rock race because it
doesn't change it's the same race every
time so you're always competing against
your best time also for H rocks the
races always take place indoors yeah so
that too I mean having a controlled
environment rather than training or
competing outside a lot of the draw in
CrossFit and a lot of what we cover C is
how a lot of the time in Elite
competitions athletes don't know what an
event will be comprised of until they're
about to do it and that information is
revealed to them and then they just have
to figure out on the Fly how to best
approach it whereas with h rock you know
exactly what you're walking into every
single time you do it and you know
exactly the number that you're probably
trying to hit because all of the
variables are controlled and I just want
to point out uh full disclosure hro has
been a sponsor of barbend properties
before right we have worked with high
rocks so just get that out of the way
all that being said when H Ro first came
onto the scene I was a little skeptical
first one I ever saw was in 2019 in New
York I was going to a different Fitness
event but they had a high rocks
competition there as well very well
attended people were raving about it I
was personally a little skeptical I was
like is it going to change between races
is the same thing over and over again
it's doing quite well I've started to
see it less as I I think part of the
problem was in my head I was comparing
it to CrossFit or comparing it to like
obstacle course racing right it's not if
you compare it to like running a half
marathon or at
10K those comparisons make a lot more
sense and then that makes its growth to
me not surprising because people do want
to kind of do it over and over again do
it with their friends Etc compare their
times with friends on different
continents the expansion into Canada is
just another sign that there is demand
for this I don't know if it if the
growth will slow anytime soon but
certainly interesting to see that hrock
is something that is has staying power
it's sticky now it's here and I think
we're going to be covering it for a
while or at least talking about it for a
while it's not just this like new thing
what is that is this going to catch on I
think it's caught on right I think the
question is how much growth can it
sustain at least that's my thinking here
yeah I think the numbers reflect that
pretty well like the this the growth is
is very steep over the last handful of
years and that trajectory doesn't seem
to be changing well folks that brings us
to the end of strength weekly we started
with powerlifting which is no running
and we ended with
eight kilometers of running uh whole
kilometers interesting narrative here
for strength weekly don't go anywhere
though or I mean go somewhere because we
won't be back for a week but we will be
back in a week to bring you more news
from around the strength game we've got
a lot of stuff coming up including the
world's strongest MMA fight a little
later this month we are just weeks out
like two weekish weeks out from the
Arnold in Columbus Ohio lots to happen
until then I'm David Thomas to joined by
Phil Blackman thanks for tuning in I
chewed on this B it's kind of gross
[Music]
sorry